A Guide to the Papers of Howard W. Smith, 1933-1966
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Howard W. Smith 1933-1966
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were given to the University of Virginia Library on October 18, 1967 by Judge Smith.
Custodial History
When Judge Smith was ready to leave his congressional offices, he called upon the National Archives and Records Service to clean out his files, and pack the materials; this is a service offered to Congressmen by NARS. NARS boxed up all the materials, and moved them across the Potomac to the Federal Records Center in Alexandria early in 1967.
Shortly thereafter, Judge Smith agreed to open his papers to the researchers of the Institute for Social Science Research, and the papers were moved a few blocks from the Federal Records Center to the third floor of Judge Smith's son's law office building where space was made available to the Institute.
The Institute staff worked through the material and removed from the boxes those papers which interested them particularly. These papers they placed in eight filing cabinets in the offices, and a card index file was prepared to assist in locating the materials. The remainder of the papers were kept in the NARS boxes and were stacked about the walls of the rooms. The collection was appraised at this time, and Mr. Robert Metzdorf's notes on the contents give a good summary of its research value.
It took the Institute fifteen or sixteen months to complete its work in the files. They made notes, and copied all materials which they found pertinent their research. By agreement with Judge Smith, the Institute has the right of prior publication of any material from the collection.
Biographical/Historical Information
Howard Worth Smith was born in Broad Run, Fauquier County, Virginia, on 2 February 1883. He attended the public schools there and was graduated from Bethel Military Academy, Warrenton, Va., in 1901. In 1903, he received his law degree from the University of Virginia, and entered the practice of law in Alexandria where he remained for the next eighteen years. He served as Commonwealth's attorney (1918-1922), judge of the corporation court (1922-1928), and judge of the 16th circuit court (1928-1930).
In 1931, he was elected to Congress from the Eighth Congressional District, and remained in office for thirty-five years. He served as chairman, Committee on Rules (Eighty-fourth through Eighty-ninth Congresses) and sponsor of the Smith Act of 1940. Smith was defeated for renomination in the Democratic primary in 1966.
Judge Smith resumed the practice of law in Alexandria, Va., where he died October 3, 1976. He was buried in Georgetown Cemetery, Broad Run, Va.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the files and working papers of Howard W. Smith who represented Virginia in Congress for some thirty-five years as representative from the Eighth Congressional District. Included are correspondence received and carbon copies of replies, clippings, printed government and other publications, copies of printed bills, reports, press releases, speeches, notes, memoranda, financial records, tape and disc recordings, drawings, and other materials. The papers cover the years 1933 to 1966 when Smith retired from Congress.
The collection is now contained in 274 Hollinger storage boxes (ca. 5"x15"x10"), one oversize box; additionally, there are eighteen looseleaf and scrapbooks, and forty-two architectural drawings. The collection fills approximately 150 shelf feet.
Smith's influence in Congress came chiefly from his early appointment to the Rules Committee. In 1955, he became its chairman, an exceedingly powerful position as the committee can determine the "length and manner of debate" on any measure moving from a committee to the floor of the House. "Although it was initially designed as a traffic committee to ease and expedite the flow of legislation in the House, the Rules Committee by postponing or refusing to grant a bill a rule bottled up measures which did not win the approval of its conservative majority." (J. Harvie Wilkinson, III, H arry Byrd and the Changing Face of Virginia Politics, 1945-1966 [Charlottesville, 1968], 71.
Other research interests which may be studied in the collection, according to Mr. Robert Metzdorf, are: "political history of Virginia, relations of the Virginia and Southern Democrats to the rest of the Democratic Party, labor unions and labor laws, lobbying, investigation of Un-Americian activities, alien registration, the Smith Act and subversion, history of the District of Columbia 1930-1966 [and legislation in Congress pertaining to it as Smith sat on the District Committee], conservation and water pollution, Selective Service and other war-time legislation, the Supreme Court and State's rights, memorials to Jefferson and Madison, the history of workmen's compensation, reappointment and the federal courts, civil rights, the Rules Committee and its role in the legislative process, the history of foreign aid, federal aid to education, the history of immigration, relation between the legislative and executive branches, the history of conservatism in the United States, 1930-1966." To these notes may be added the study of unique northern Virginia politics, patronage, and the continuing work of a Congressman in relation to his colleagues and in particular to his constituents. There does not appear to be much material in the collection which shows Smith's relation to Senator Harry Byrd in the political sense, although there is interesting correspondence. Naturally, the collection will be the basis for any biography of Judge Smith, an important historical task which, hopefully, will be undertaken soon.
Arrangement
Series I: Bills Introduced in Congress by Judge Smith Boxes 1-12 In general, this series comprises a chronological arrangement by Congress, and an alphabetical series of topics within each Congress. The folders usually contain a copy of the printed bill plus pertinent correspondence, notes, and other helpful material.
Series II: Miscellaneous Legislation Boxes 13-111 This series comprises a chronological series by Congress with an alphabetical arrangement of topics within each Congress. There is generally one folder for each topic, but occasionally there are more. The folders contain correspondence, notes, printed materials, copies of the printed bill, and anything Judge Smith or his staff found pertinent. When material identified as belonging to an earlier Congress appears under a later one, it has been left where it was found on the presumption that the legislation may have carried over or that it was placed there for good reason. Note especially the sub-series on Civil rights in boxes 100-111.
Series III: Miscellaneous Correspondence Boxes 112-187 Boxes 112-187
Again, the arrangement in this series is by Congress, and within the Congress, the arrangement is alphabetical. The series begins with the 84th Congress. The topics range from the Democratic National Committee to the Fish and Wildlife Service.
Series IV: Private Bills Boxes 188, 189 Bills introduced by Smith "for the relief of" constituents or other private individuals.
Series V: Speeches, Articles, Recordings, Etc. Boxes 190-193; [oversize box] This series contains offprints of articles by and about Smith, copies of the Congressional Record containing Smith's speeches in "Congress, and other publications containing interviews with, or articles by Smith. Drafts and texts of speeches by Smith are found. The materials are arranged by Congress. There are a number of tape and disc recordings of speeches by Smith, or interviews of him.
Series VI: Campaign Record Boxes 194-210 In this series are found campaign literature, clippings, returns, correspondence with workers and supporters, lists of votes, expense accounts, research files on hi sopponents and their remarks, and folders on areas in Smith's district. Also present are folders on other Virginia elections, and some materials on national elections. The file is organized chronologically by the campaign beginnings with 1938, but materials are sparce until 1950.
Series VII: Endorsement and Patronage Correspondence Boxes 211-213 This correspondence is filed chronologically by the Congress, and alphabetically within the Congress, and covers the 83rd to 89th Congresses.
Series VIII: Correspondence re Petitions; Qualified Voters Boxes 214-217 Arranged by area within his district. Last two boxes contain mailing lists of qualified voters.
Series IX: National Labor Relations Board Files Boxes 219-229 An alphabetical file of materials generated by the Special Committee of the House headed by Smith which investigated the NLRB, 1939-1942. Three scrapbooks, listed at the end of the listings of boxes in this inventory, contain pertinent newspaper clippings and cartoons. For Smith's continuing interest in labor legislation, one should consult Series 1 and 2.
Series X: Strasbourg Conference Records Boxes 230, 231 Smith attended the conference held in Strasbourg in 1951 to discuss problems common to Europe and North America as a member of the U.S. delegation. most of the records in this series are printed reports and debates, but there are a few clippings and letters.
Series XI: Virginia Post Office Correspondence Boxes 232-254 This series contains an alphabetical arrangement by the name of the post office of correspondence concerning postmasterships, location of new post offices and the like. Much patronage material appears here.
Series XII: Service Academies Correspondence Boxes 255-264 A chronological series with folders for each academy for each year beginning with 1945, re appointments.
Series XIII: Thomas Jefferson Memorial Commission Records Boxes 265-270 This series contains, in no particular order, records of the work of the Commission appointed to determine a suitable memorial to Thomas Jefferson in Washington, D.C. There are minutes of the meetings of the commission, blue prints, correspondence, printed materials, etc. One should also note the existance of the architectural drawings submitted in competition for the design award. These are listed separately at the end of the listings of the contents of the boxes of the main collection.
Series XIV: Miscellaneous Files Boxes 271-274 Miscellaneous files, and clippings and articles about Smith.
Series XV: Scrapbooks This is a series of books, 1938-1966, filled with clippings about Smith and his career, organized chronologically, with some miscellaenous books at the end.
Series XVI: Thomas Jefferson Memorial Architectural Competition Drawings
Contents List
- Series I: Bills Introduced in Congress by Smith
  - Resolution on Impeachment of Judge Lowell - 73rd Congress Lowell Procedure (Box 1)
  - Alien Bill - 76th Congress (Box 1)
  - H. Report No. 374 re: boundary line between D.C. and Va. (Box 1)
  - Alien Registration - Support of Organizations (Box 1)
  - Alien Registration - Extracts from Cong. Record (Box 1)
  - H. R. 61066 - Labor Bill - correspondence (Box 2)
  - H. R. 6616 - out of state correspondence pertaining thereto (Box 2)
  - H. R. 6616 - letters from State of Virginia (Box 2)
  - Lobby Bill-H.R. 262-75th Congress (Box 3)
  - H. R. 6790-Labor-77th Congress (Box 3)
  - H. R. 6149-Labor-77th Congress (Box 3)
  - H.R. 6066-Labor (Box 3)
    Anti-Strike Bill-77th Congress
  - Green, William (Labor) (Box 3)
  - H. R. 6616-Regarding continuing debate on Floor-77th Congress (Box 3)
  - H.R. 6284-to provide for emergency operation of mines, plants, and facilities essential to public health -80th Congress (Box 3)
  - H.R. 4789-to permit Navy Bands to furnish music for charitable and patritic functions-79th Congress (Box 3)
  - H. R. 3937-to repeal War Labor Disputes Act and abolish National war Labor Board (Box 3)
  - H.R. 4796-to permit Army bands to furnish music for charitable and patriotic functions (Box 3)
  - H.R. 312-to amend Sec. 702 of Title 34 of U.S. Code-79th Congress (Box 3)
  - H.R. 313 - to amend Sec. 905 of Title 10 of U.S. Code - 80th Congress (Box 3)
  - H.R. 310-Falls Church Water System-80th Congress (Box 3)
  - H.R. 311-to authorize the Sec. of War to permit the delivery of water from Washington aqueduct pumping station to Falls Church (Box 3)
  - Connally-Smith Bill-Analysis of (Box 3)
  - H.R. 3937-to Repeal Smith-Connally Act - 80th Congress (Box 3)
  - Speech in Congressional Record, 4 June 1943-Analysis of Connally-smith bill passed by House (Box 3)
  - Federal Communication Comm. Report-June 1, 1949 (Box 3)
  - 81st Congress
    - H.R. 1432-re: Alexandria Commeorative Stamp (Box 4)
    - H.R. 1937-To provide additional revenue for D.C. (Box 4)
    - H.R. 2153-Commeorative Stamp for Culpeper Co. 200th Anniversary (Box 4)
    - H.R. 3297-Addition of Lands to Manassas Battlefield (Box 4)
    - H.R. 4502-To authorize Sec. of Army to dispose of certain easement near Ft. Belvoir, Virginia (Box 4)
    - H.R. 455-to amend Rule XIII (Box 4)
    - H.R. 475-Reading of George Washing Address (Box 4)
    - H. Joint Res. - to investigate strikes (Box 4)
    - H.R. 8001-to amend Act to define real property exempt from taxation in D.C. (Box 4)
    - H.R. 8106-to amend D.C. Teachers Salary Act of 1947 (Box 4)
    - H.R. 8372-to amend D.C. Tax Laws (Box 4)
    - H.R. 8578-Authorizing loans from U.S. Treasurer for expansion of D.C. Water system (Box 4)
    - H.R. 9251-to fix responsibility of disbursing officer and D. C. Auditor (Box 4)
    - H.R. 1065-to name Twin Highway bridges over Potomac (Box 4)
    - H.R. 1066-to fix responsibility of disbursing officer and Auditor in D.C. (Box 4)
    - H.R. 1067-Tomb of Unkown Soldier of Revolution (Box 4)
    - H.R. 1068-Extension of Park, Parkway and Playground System of National Capital and Virginia (Box 4)
    - H.R. 1901-to provide for disposal of Nevius Tract at Public Sale (Box 4)
    - H.R. 2256-to amend the Railroad Retirement Act of 1937 (Box 4)
    - H.R. 2327-prince William Forest Park (Box 4)
    - H.R. 2530-to amend certain tax laws applicable to D.C. (Box 4)
    - Congressional Record, Jan; Feb. 9, 1950-re: Aid to Korea and Economic Aid to Asia (Box 4)
  - 82nd Congress
    - H.R. 1066-to fix responsibilities of the Disbursing Officer and Auditor of D. C. (Box 5)
    - H.R. 2256-to amend Railroad Retirement Act of 1937 (Box 5)
    - H.R. 2530-to amend D.C. tax laws (Box 5)
    - H.R. 2658-to amend Selective Service Act of 1948 (Box 5)
    - H.R. 2954-For bridge over Potomac from Shepherds Landing (Box 5)
    - H.R. 3462-Sewerage disposal for Virginia through D.C. Plant (Box 5)
    - H.R. 5235 - to investigate for construction of bridge over Potomac River at Shepherds Landing (Box 5)
    - H.R. 5256-to secure attendance of witnesses in D.C. in criminal proceedings (Box 5)
    - H.R. 4058-National Capital Region-to provide for growth of (Box 5)
    - H.R. 5235-to make studies and investigate location and construction of bridge over Potomac River to Shepherds Landing (Box 5)
    - H.R. 6676-to amend D. C. Tax Law (Box 5)
    - H.R. 6811-to amend Tax on Motor Vehicle fuels in D.C. (Box 5)
    - H.R. 6963-education facilities to children living adjacent to Federal property (Box 5)
    - H.R. 7034-to amend Code Law of D.C. (Box 5)
    - H.R. 7502-to amend act relating to Park and National Capital Parl Commission (Box 5)
    - H. Con. Res. 210-Condemning President's action in seizing steel companies (Box 5)
    - Smith Amendment to Defense Production Act (requesting President to invoke Taft-Hartley Act in Steel Strike) (Box 5)
    - H.R. 7647-to protect the National Defense against consequences of certain labor disputes-folder of correspondence re H.R. 7647 (Box 5)
    - Copies of Bills introduced by Judge Smith in 82nd Congress (Box 5)
  - 83rd Congress
    - H. Con. Res. 28-Westmoreland County Anniversary (Box 6)
    - H. R. 3380-exchange of lands for Prince William Forest Park (Box 6)
    - H.R. 4226-commercial parking in D.C. (Box 6)
    - H. Joint Res.-amendments relative to making of treaties and executive agreements (Box 6)
    - Cong. Record -March 9, 1953, "Hawaii Should Not Be Admitted to Statehood" (Box 6)
  - 84th Congress
    - H.R. 11756-to amend legislation re: Payment of cost and expense of constructing a railway and highway grade eleimination structure in D.C. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 7772-funds for construction of certain highway, railroad grade elimination structure in D.C. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 7783-to authorize Philadelphia Baltimore and Washington R. R. Co. to construct, maintain and operate a branch track or siding over 2nd Street, S.E., D.C. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 7968-Curreoman Bay, Va., Public Works Committee bill (Box 6)
    - Printed copies of bills introduced by Smith (Box 6)
    - H.R. 325-Howard, Erwin B. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 4532-to amend D.C. sales and use tax (Box 6)
    - H.R. 7217-to provide revenue for D.C. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 8168-to provide revenue for D.C. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 8284-to incorporate the George Washington Boyhood Home (Box 6)
    - H.R. 9641-to exempt from taxation certain property of the Columbia Historical Society in the D.C. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 9770-to provide revenue for D.C. (Box 6)
    - H.R. 3 - to establish rules of interpretation governing questions of the effect of Acts of Congress on state laws (Box 6)
    - H.R. 1969-to survey Windmill Pt., Lancaster Co., Va. (Box 6)
  - 85th Congress
    - H.R. 8823-Commission on Presidential office space (Box 7)
    - H.R. 2509-to amend the Alcoholic Beverage Control Act of D.C. of 1934 (Box 7)
    - H.R. 2510-to amend the Alcoholic Beverage Control Act of D.C. of 1934 (Box 7)
    - H.R. 4836-to provide for examination, licensing and regulation of dispensing opticians and optical technicians in D.C. (Box 7)
    - H.R. 5498-to amend the Act of D.C. to increase amount (Box 7)
    - H.R. 5966-to amend the act entitled "An Act to regulate the practice of optometry in D.C." (Box 7)
    - H.R. 7104-to amend D.C. income and franchise Tax Act of 1947 as amended by providing additional person exemption for resident income tax payers and their spouses who are blind (Box 7)
    - H.R. 7248-to amend D.C. Income and franchise Tax Act of 1947 to provide that under certain conditions officers of the Executive branch of the Federal government appointed by the President shall be exempt from such Act (Box 7)
    - H.R. 7265-to amend D.C. and Franchise Tax Act of 1947, to exclude Social Security benefits and to provide additional exemptions for age and blindness (Box 7)
    - H.R. 7467-to amend the Act of March 3, 1901 with respect to the Citizenship residence qualifications of the Directors or Trustees of certain companies in D.C. (Box 7)
    - H.R. 7835-to increase authorization for Hospital Center and Facilities in D.C. (Box 7)
    - Cong. Record -July 27, 1939 (Box 7)
    - H.R. 8256 - to amend D.C. Income and Franchise Tax Act of 1947 to exclude Social Security benefits and to provide additional exemptions and to except from personal property taxation any D.C. boats used solely for pleasure purposes (Box 7)
    - H.R. 8871-Sibley Hospital (Box 7)
    - H.R. 8918-Sibley Hospital (Box 7)
    - H.R. 7249-to improve and extend, through reciprocal legislation, the enforcement of support in D.C. (Box 7)
    - H.R. 9271-to authorize National Society of American Revolution to use certain real estate in D.C. as National Headquarters (Box 7)
    - H. Joint Res. 421-James Monroe Bicentennial (Box 7)
    - H.R. 12377-to authorize Commissioners of D.C. to borrow funds for capital improvement programs (Box 7)
    - H.R. 13628-to amend Sec. 2, b. 5 of D.C. Income and Franchise Tax of 1947 (Box 7)
    - H.R. 3413-to improve and extend duties of support in D.C. (Box 7)
    - H.R. 5965-to improve and extend duties of support in D.C. (Box 7)
    - H.R. 6127-to provide for securing and protection civil rights (Box 7)
    - H.R. 8361-to amend section 2254 of Title 28, U.S. Code (Box 7)
    - H.R. 12969-to authorize the delivery of sewage from Virginia into sewerage system of D.C. (Box 8)
    - H. Joint Res. 449-proposing amendment to Constitution with respect ot admission of new state as soverign states of U.S. (Box 8)
    - H.R. 119-(formerly H.R. 462) Committee on Administrative Procedure and Practices (Box 8)
    - Bills Judge [Smith] Introduced in 85th Congress (Box 8)
  - 86th Congress
    - H. Joint R. 458-James Monroe Memorial (Box 8)
    - H.R. 7507-to amend Sec. 3 of Title III of D.C. Income and Franchise Tax with respect to deductions for charitable contributions (Box 8)
    - H.R. 6929-expense of Government of D.C. for Fiscal Year 1911 (Box 8)
    - H.R. 6378-to authorize Society of International Law to use certain real estate in D.C. as Nation Hqs. (Box 8)
    - H. Joint R. 412-to authorize National Geographic Society to erect a memorial to Rear Admiral Richard E. Byrd (Box 8)
    - H.R. 12073-to authoirze D.C. Commission to use sanitary sewer to connect the Dulles International Airport with D.C. (Box 8)
  - 87th Congress
    - H.R. 10222-to authorize coinage of 50¢ pieces commemorating 200th Anniversary of Charlottesville, Va. (Box 8)
    - H.R. 12184-D.C. Redevelopment (Box 8)
    - H.R. 11515-D.C. Motor Vehicle Safety (Box 8)
    - H.R. 11516-D.C. Motor Vehicle Safety (Box 8)
    - H.R. 5227-to amend D.C. Business Corporation Act (Box 8)
    - H.R. 5681-to amend D.C. Unemployment Compensation Act (Box 8)
    - H.R. 5127-to amend Sec. 131 of Title 23 U.S. code to control advertising, in areas adjacent to interstate system (Box 8)
    - H.R. 8460-D.C. Railroad siding (Box 8)
    - Bills Judge [Smith] is going to reintroduce in 87th Congress (Box 8)
    - H.R. 3-States Rights (Box 8)
    - H.R. 106-Clause 2 of Rule XXI (Box 8)
    - H.R. 185-to amend rule XIII of the House (Box 8)
    - H.R. 2537-to permit state officers to participate in political activity without loss of federal funds (Box 8)
    - H.R. 3092-to amend section ? of Title 28 U.S. Code (Box 8)
    - H.R. 3093-to amend section ? of Title 28 U.S. Code (Box 8)
    - H.R. 3094-to amend section ? of Title 28 U.S. Code (Box 8)
    - H.R. 3216-to amend section 2254 of U.S. Code re: habeas corpus (Box 8)
    - H.R. 3217-to amend section 1332 ? of Title 28 of U.S. Code re: diversity of citizenship (Box 8)
  - 88th Congress
    - H.R. 106-resolution to change House rules (Box 9)
    - H.R. 192-Salem Church Dam-84th Congress (Box 9)
    - H.R. 97-Withdrawal of money from the Treasury (Back-door Spending)-88th Congress (Box 9)
    - Printed copies of bills introduced by Smith (Box 9)
    - H.R. 456-create commission to investigate research programs by departments and agencies of government (Box 10)
    - See note in File-note not found (Box 10)
    - H. Joint R. 294-amending Section 201 (a) Budget & Acct. (Box 10)
      Act of 1921-88th Congress
    - H.R. 1835-Writ of Habeas Corpus (Box 10)
    - H.R. 1833-U.S. Commissioners (Box 10)
    - H.R. 7152-to enforce right to vote (Rep. Cellar) (Box 10)
  - 89th Congress
    - H.R. 16590-tax treatment of gifts to charities (Box 11)
    - H.R. 228-relating to Germanesse (Box 11)
    - H.R. 1164-consent of Congress to amend Virginia, Maryland and D.C. Metropolitan Area Transit Regulation Compact-89th Congress (Box 11)
    - H.R. 15645-exclude from income certain reimbursed moving expenses-89th Congress-2nd Session (Box 11)
    - H.R. 9699-authorize D.C. to sell certain property in Prince William County-87th Congress (Box 11)
    - H.R. 7488-authorize use of certain real property in D.C. for Chancery (Box 11)
    - H.R. 11732-Washington County National Parkway (Box 12)
    - H. Joint R. 685-(Dr. Mahlon Loomis) (Box 12)
    - Salem Church Dam, Ref. etc. (Box 12)
- Series II: Miscellaneous Legislation
  - Agriculture (Box 13)
    84th Congress
  - Alien (Box 13)